<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 13. of Iune. 1602. By M. Francis Marburie</title>
            <title>Sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 13. of June. 1602.</title>
            <author>Marbury, Francis, d. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105434</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841162</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841162</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 929:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 13. of Iune. 1602. By M. Francis Marburie</title>
                  <title>Sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 13. of June. 1602.</title>
                  <author>Marbury, Francis, d. 1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[90] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short, and are to be sold [by C. Burby] in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A1) B-F(-F7-8).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:1"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Paules Croſſe the 13. <hi>of Iune,</hi> 1602.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Geneſ. 9. verſ. 27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord ſhall allure Iapheth, and he ſhall dwel in the tents of Shem, and Canaan ſhall be their ſeruant.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that <hi>Moſes</hi> had finiſhed the ſtorie of the drowning of the old world, he begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſpeake of the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the earth to <hi>Noah</hi> againe. And he mentioneth the thankfulnes of <hi>Noah</hi> and the bleſſing of God vpon him and his, by beſtowing both benefits, lawes and promiſes vpon them. By name he proſpered the handie worke of <hi>Noah</hi> in the vineyard which hee had planted.
<pb facs="tcp:5724:2"/>And by occaſion thereof, is chronicled <hi>Noahs</hi> fall by infirmity into drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the little regard which he had of his honour in his drunkennes, which appeared by his diſcouering of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the middeſt of his tent. From hence (as it followeth) his ſonne <hi>Cham</hi> tooke occaſion to diſhonour him, both by impious lookes, to the forfeiture of his owne reuerence, &amp; alſo by impious and ſcornefull report of that he ſaw, to draw his brethren to the like. But he fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of his purpoſe: for <hi>Shem</hi> being affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with due piety, as the author of this filiall dutie, and <hi>Iapheth</hi> being induced by his brother <hi>Shem</hi> to be a readie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adiutor in the ſame, came to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of their fathers diſhonour: and throwing his garment that lay by vpon their ſhoulders, with their faces from him, couered him with the ſame, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their reuerence vnto him, by not ſeeing. When <hi>Noah</hi> awooke, and his drunkennes was clean departed, &amp; had
<pb facs="tcp:5724:2"/>receiued ſome informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſomeway) of the matter concerning the behauiour of his ſonnes, all perturbation of mind remoued, as became the Prophet of the Lord, he was moued by the holy Ghoſt to publiſh vnto them by way of oracle, what ſhould ſeuerally befall them after this deede, eſpecially in their proſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. So this oracle hath the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the full recouerie of his ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and of his due notice of the cauſe. And firſt, as the vengeance of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chams</hi> impietie (who before is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cham</hi> the father of <hi>Canaan</hi>) he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth a curſe againſt this <hi>Canaan</hi> being <hi>Chams</hi> ſonne,<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> becauſe (as <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> ſuppoſeth) this <hi>Canaan</hi> abuſed his grandfather to, (I know not vpon what ground) or rather becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> from Gods oracle (not to bee examined by mans rule) purpoſed to make the name of the Canaanites odious to the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, for whom he wrote this ſtorie, as they were now on their iourney to the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>land of Canaan to winne it.</p>
            <p>The curſe hee denounceth againſt <hi>Canaan</hi> is,<note place="margin">Gen. 10.21.</note> that <hi>he ſhall be a ſeruant of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to his brethren.</hi> The other two (which are after called <hi>brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> for their ioyning in this deed) hee ioyneth in a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Firſt hee bleſſeth <hi>Shem</hi> the authour thereof, though otherwiſe yonger then <hi>Iapheth.</hi> In his behalfe hee bleſſeth the Lord in a right feruent bleſſing, as for ſome high benefit reueiled. Giuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titling intimation in his bleſſing, that Chriſt ſhould deſcend of him, in whoſe ly alſo from that time forward true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion continued.</p>
            <p>Next, he bleſſeth in this text <hi>Iapheth Shems</hi> helper in this worke of pietie. Him he bleſſeth in his poſteritie, that is, in the Gentiles, which ſhould dwell far diſtant in Aſia and Europe, as <hi>Rupertus</hi> obſerueth ſpecially; for as for the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Iewes that he meaneth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions bordering on the holy land, it may
<pb facs="tcp:5724:3"/>go amongſt the reſt of their vanities. He prophecieth then, that howſoeuer ſome generations of <hi>Iapheths</hi> ofſpring ſhould grow wild and barbarous, and forſake the religion of <hi>Shem;</hi> yet the time ſhould come that the Lord by the vertue of his Spirit would reclaime the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and call them home to his grace. And that he would worke vpon their wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fierceneſſe with his ſweet and amiable allurements of the Goſpell, and as it were to breake their hearts with kindneſſe, to draw them both to returne, and alſo to abide in the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> Speaking after their maner of dwelling then, but meaning that the Gentiles (whereof, as I haue ſaid, a good part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of <hi>Iapheth</hi>) ſhould be wonne to the religion of Chriſt the ſon of <hi>Shem</hi> in Gods fatherly pietie to them; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his eternall election, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the grace and filiall pietie that God wrought in their father <hi>Iapheth,</hi> when he holpe <hi>Shem</hi> to couer his father
<pb facs="tcp:5724:4"/>
               <hi>Noah.</hi> For fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence God moued <hi>Noah</hi> to promiſe <hi>Iapheth</hi> thus much as from the occaſion, but not the cauſe of this bleſſing. And further he promiſeth to <hi>Iapheth</hi> (as before he promiſed to <hi>Shem</hi>) that <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhal be his ſeruant, becauſe they ſhould both ſucceſſiuely partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate in this dominion ouer <hi>Canaan</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed hath it plurally in both places.) But <hi>Iapheth</hi> hath this differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, firſt, that <hi>Canaan,</hi> which is promiſed to be his ſeruant, is not to bee vnderſtood literally, but is to be taken (vnder that name) for the enemies wherewith the Church of the Gentiles in generall ſhould be annoyed. And ſecondly, that the ſeruitude of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhall be annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Iapheths</hi> dwelling with <hi>Shem,</hi> and ſo conditionall to <hi>Iapheth</hi> to continue during his continuance in the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> Thus the promiſe hath two parts, the firſt that he ſhall communicate with <hi>Shem</hi> in the couenant, ſignified by dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Shems</hi> tents and the ſecond that
<pb facs="tcp:5724:4"/>he ſhall participate with <hi>Shem</hi> in ruling ouer the enemies of the church, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Canaans</hi> ſeruitude vnder him.</p>
            <p>So this text is, diſpoſed into two parts, that is, into two promiſes. The propoſition of the former promiſe is that <hi>Iapheth,</hi> that is, <hi>Iapheths</hi> poſteritie, according to his name, which ſignifieth allurable, ſhall ſhew himſelfe a <hi>Iapheth,</hi> that is, allurable, and ſhall receiue a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Which is deſcribed firſt from the author, <hi>The Lord:</hi> ſecondly, from the meanes, <hi>ſhall allure Iapheth:</hi> thirdly, by the effect, <hi>that hee may dwell in the tents of Shem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propoſition of the latter promiſe is, that <hi>Canaan ſhall bee their ſeruant,</hi> where <hi>Canaan</hi> is put figuratiuely. And this firſt is inferred with that Hebrue copulatine <hi>Vau,</hi> which is of ſo many ſignifications, and here ſtandeth for <hi>Le magnan,</hi> as it doth Leu. 18.5. <hi>Let a man keepe my ſtatutes and he ſhall liue in them,</hi> that is, <hi>Then</hi> (as it is wel rendred) or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5724:5"/>that condition. Secondly, it is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnder the tearme of ſeruant, which ſignifieth one that is held from hauing intereſt in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>As if <hi>Noah</hi> had extended this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend breuity into a larger diſcourſe thus. As I haue already partly in the right of a father, and more amply in the dutie of a Prophet bleſſed my ſonne <hi>Shem</hi> for his pietie to me, wherein hee was the principal: ſo now likewiſe in the like right and dutie, I bleſſe my ſonne <hi>Iapheth</hi> his coadiutor. To whom as by Gods direction I gaue the name of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth,</hi> which carieth the ſignification of aptneſſe to be allured, ſo I prophecie to him in the behalfe of his poſteritie, that he ſhall in it (anſwerably to his name) be allured in the good part to good, as my ſon here hath now been by his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Shem</hi> in this worke of pietie to me. For although there ſhall be a long and a grieuous departing away of <hi>Iapheths</hi> poſteritie from <hi>Shem,</hi> with whom ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5724:5"/>remaine the truth of religion with the oracles thereof, &amp; of whom the <hi>Meſsiah</hi> ſhall deſcend: ſo that their Gentiliſme and idolatrie ſhall alienate them, and Satan ſhall a long time entiſe in the ill part from the true God of <hi>Shem,</hi> ſo farre that they ſhall be paſt all mans recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: yet the time in due ſeaſon ſhal come that the Lord himſelfe ſhall take the matter into his hands, and by the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent vertue of his holy Spirit ſhall conuert them. And for the manner of conuerting them, it ſhal not be done by violence, but (as I ſaid) by entiſing, and by the ſweete allurements of almightie God, euen by the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and the godly endeuours of the ſeruants of Chriſt, who ſhall both by their life and doctrine allure them. And theſe are the meanes which the Lord will ſanctifie by the might and grace of his holy Spirit to their conuerſion. And wherto ſhall the Lord allure <hi>Iapheth?</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to dwel in the tents of <hi>She<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is, in
<pb facs="tcp:5724:6"/>the Church of Chriſt which is the ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of felicitie and the greateſt benefit that God can beſtow on man, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is the mirrour of wretchedneſſe. In theſe tents of <hi>Shem</hi> the Lord ſhall allure them to dwell, that is, they ſhall come thither, and abide there when they are come: ſo that the Church ſhall not be remoued from the Gentiles, though ſome parts thereof ſhall be greatly ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed. And this ſhall be the firſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to communicate with <hi>Shem</hi> in the bleſſing of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>And to this there ſhall be added a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond bleſſing, wherein he ſhall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with <hi>Shem</hi> likewiſe, by ſucceſſion from the Iewes to the Gentiles: and that is in the dominion ouer ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church, as ſhall be in their ſeuerall times. For as the verie nation of the Canaanites ſhal be ſubiect to the Iewes, which deſcended of <hi>Shem:</hi> ſo thoſe which ſhall ſucceed the Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites in enmitie to Gods Church, of
<pb facs="tcp:5724:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nation ſoeuer they be, ſhall bee brought in ſubiection. And their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection ſhall conſiſt not only in ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them from vſurping authoritie, but alſo from vſurping libertie and impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in their maliciouſneſſe. And this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond bleſſing ſhall be ſo annexed to the former, that it cannot be enioyed apart. But ſo long as <hi>Iapheth</hi> ſhall dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> ſo long ſhall <hi>Canaan</hi> bee their ſeruant. But when their loue of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall quaile, their enimies ſhall preuaile againſt them.</p>
            <p>This is the expoſition of this oracle: now it remaineth to make our obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions according to it: and there are ſixe concluſions to bee drawne out of this Text.</p>
            <p>The firſt concluſion is, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that whereas <hi>Noah</hi> vrgeth <hi>Iapheths</hi> poſteritie with an argument taken out of the ſignification of his name <hi>Iapheth,</hi> wherewith alſo hee poliſheth his ſpeech ſaying, <hi>Iepth Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth,</hi> as much as (by like agnominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)
<pb facs="tcp:5724:7"/>the <hi>allurable ſhall bee allured,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ghoſt propoundeth vnto vs thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the edification of names, that it is our duty to edifie our ſelues by thoſe names of importance, which the Lord by his prouidence &amp; ordinance hath allotted vnto vs. And amongſt the reſt by this particular name of <hi>Iapheth</hi> (which is ours by deſcent) to edifie our ſelues in the grace of tractableneſſe and eaſineſſe to be allured to our owne good, that we may be <hi>Iapheths</hi> indeede, as well as in name. The holy Scriptures are found to haue a great felicitie in theſe notations &amp; agnominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in their originall, both by the like ſound of words which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed well, and alſo for the deriuations ſake, as thoſe that can skill may ſee in many places of the originall. Thus it is Zepan. 2.4. thus Iſai. 24.4. thus Act. 8.30 thus Rom. 12.3. and thus Iacob in his bleſſing both decketh his ſpeech, and alſo maketh matter of the ſeuerall names of the Patriarkes, Genel. 49. And
<pb facs="tcp:5724:7"/>yet alwayes with the ſobrietie of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not giuing libertie to make mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Etymologies without a cauſe, nor to be vaine in affecting the ſound of words, but ſhewing their completenes in ioyning ſweet and profitable toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Specially this is ſo in theſe ample Oracles, which were certain<note n="*" place="margin">Holy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings.</note> Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicks (as they were wont to call other conceits) in the Church of God grauen in the memory with a diuine skil. Heere the holy ghoſt diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth with the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the word, for the pleaſant affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: for to ſay the truth, this verb <hi>Iepht</hi> properly ſignifieth to intiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> il part, or to deceiue, as Exo. 22.16. but becauſe it ſweetly ſoundeth with the name of <hi>Iapheth,</hi> he vſeth it in the good part. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this name of <hi>Iapheth</hi> which we haue now vnder hand, wherewith the holy ghoſt chargeth the conſcience of the Gentiles of Europe deſcended from him to whom the goſpell is tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and amongſt the reſt ſpecially of
<pb facs="tcp:5724:8"/>theſe verie Ilands (as ſome men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to particularize) it ought to moue vs (as we haue ſaid) to tractablenes, that there be not a ſtubborne and vnflexible mind in vs that will not be allured to true religion, that we be not (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) <hi>Like the deafe Adder that will not heare the voice of the charmer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>though he charme neuer ſo cunningly.</hi> We muſt (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>cauſe our eares</hi> perforce <hi>to heare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>and encline our hearts to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> It is an heauie iudgement of God to be hard hearted. This ſinne is the puniſhment of another ſinne, euen of continuance in ſinne. And it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakablie horrible to be giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe, that is, to hold a lie in our right hand after demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the truth. He is indeed a foole (as <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſaith) <hi>that beleeueth euerie thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and is caried vp and downe with euerie wind of doctrine.</hi> But he is a worſe and more wofull foole that ſheweth his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractablenes againſt God, and his ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornnes
<pb facs="tcp:5724:8"/>againſt his word whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he goeth about to reclaime him. There is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtifnes to be ſtiffe in the truth. The Papiſts defame the land with a pretence of praiſe, that they find many tractable perſons in the ſame: but who ſo is of a wiſe heart will diſdaine the deuils pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and will remember that amongſt whoremongers auſteritie is the defence of chaſtitie. Well I am ſure that there are many poiſoned with a preiudice againſt the religion of Ieſus Chriſt, and they will not heare with any patience what may be ſaid for the truth. And there are againe which although they will heare, will not be perſwaded to an effectuall conuerſion. Moued they are, but not remoued. The ſtifnecked Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts if they will ſuffer themſelues to beare their denomination where they haue their dependence (I means of the Pope) are grieuous offenders in this kind, by name in this ſinne of obfirming &amp; hardening themſelues againſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb facs="tcp:5724:9"/>and perſwaſion. They haue the propertie of the Adders before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Pſalme, which (as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> and <hi>Caſsiodorus</hi> ſay) make a ſhift with the earth on the one ſide, and their taile on the other, to ſtop both eares, that they may not be charmed. Obfirmation is a Cardinall tradition of poperie, and in this they are ſo reſolute that they will turne to anie ſhift rather then be perſwaded by the truth. Firſt, ſome will not heare. Secondly, ſome wil not confer. Thirdly, ſome that will reaſon wil not yeeld when they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe they are ouercome, but wil lay the blame in their owne vnskilfulnes, &amp; the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their aduerſary, whom they referre to thoſe of their ſide that are better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues remain obſtinate. Fourthly, ſome will be tried by certaine writers, and then if they be taken in their owne ſnare, they will pretend ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery in the impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (they muſe as they vſe, as their <hi>index expurgatorius</hi> beareth
<pb facs="tcp:5724:9"/>mention.) Fiftly, others will ſtand vpon a Doctor where his expoſition may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage them; and otherwhere when they are like to be loſers by his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, they depoſe him &amp; appeale to the expoſition of the Church. Sixtly, they will authoriſe bookes, as <hi>Montanus, Ianſenius, Ferus,</hi> and other, they will permit others to bee printed by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And if there be aduantage for the Proteſtants in either, then (forſooth) they are iudgements of particular men and not of the Church. To be briefe, whatſoeuer the text ſaith, or whatſoeuer the gloſſe ſaith, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at the firſt both text and gloſſe be of their owne edition and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if they fall not out to ſerue their turne, they will contradict them. For they are reſolued to be Papiſts ſtill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no <hi>Iapheths,</hi> but of an vnreachable ſpirit. They are for great Clarkes ſold to the world by their oſtentation of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts, but their mayn ground is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy.
<pb facs="tcp:5724:10"/>They are ſo farre from yeelding themſelues to the ſpirit of God, that they be not gouerned by the common ſenſe of man which is reaſon; but by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe of beaſts, which is wil. We ſtand all before the Lord, in whoſe ſight it is damnably dangerous to beare falſe witneſſe either againſt Papiſts or other, if any be worſe then they. Al this which we haue ſpoken is vnder the manifolde experience of many, and they are a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration which may inure vs to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pray for vs that we may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from euill and abſurd men, for all haue not faith.</hi> Nay they are ſo farre from faith, and ſo hardned in infidelitie, that they wil not be allured by God himſelfe. They haue caſt the word of the Lord behind them, <hi>and they ſhall ſee</hi> (as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> ſaith) <hi>what wil come of it at the laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this for thoſe Papiſts that are more ſtubborne and reſolute. Now there are others moued (as I ſaid) but not remoued, which although they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:5724:10"/>to ſhew ſome ſigne of flexiblenes when means are made to them, yet they perſiſt not in a tractable ſpirit. They come part of the way by ſome worke of conſcience within them, but they are ſoone drawn backe againe. The reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sathan is ſtronger with them then the vocation of God. Theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue great need to looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; to examine duely what kind of ſinne this may bee which is in them, which cauſeth theſe fearefull relapſes either in their religion or in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. The examination is this. If a man cannot bee effectually enticed to hate ſinne, it is to be imputed to the fleſh which reſiſteth the grace of God. And this cauſe is to be conſidered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to be, either becauſe the fleſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth <hi>in him,</hi> that hindreth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of his ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though it be begun, or elſe becauſe he is <hi>in the fleſh</hi> &amp; hath no true grace begun in him at al.</p>
            <p>And if wee affect to be of the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:5724:11"/>kind, let vs mortifie our corruption and the vnteachablenes of our carnall man. And if we feare to bee of the ſecond, let vs terrifie our ſelues from that conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the word of God which ſaith, that <hi>they that are in the fleſh ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not pleaſe God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.8.</note> now (if there be any other inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to be ſetled in popery is to be in the fleſh. And let vs remember the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Simon</hi> the witch &amp; S. <hi>Peters</hi> cenſure of him. His exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple is that being ſo far conuerted that he was baptized, he reuolted ſo farre that he offered to buy the holy ghoſt to play the impoſtor. Saint <hi>Peters</hi> cenſure is not that the gall of bitternes was ſo deepely ſetled in him that it was not cleane purged out: but I ſee (ſaith hee) that thou art ſet <hi>in the gall of bitternes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8, 23</note> For theſe two ſinnes differ as much one from another, as his caſe in whoſe belly the water is ſtill after that he hath beene pulled out of the ſea, and his that himſelfe is ſtill in the water and ouerwhelmed with the ſea.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:11"/>
            <p>The times are verie enticing to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in religion, as they were before the floud. At that time the holy Ghoſt ſaith, they that had any ſyncerity in them began more effectually <hi>to call on the name of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.26.</note> as we read in the 4. of Gen. or to bee called or entitled after the name of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> as we are now enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after the name of Chriſt. They bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when they ſaw the reſt of the world to fly off from the Church, to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate &amp; to flock to the church of God. Is it not a venerable preſident for theſe daungerous times? And if euer there were a time for thoſe that are newters by infirmitie, and haue caried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues looſely &amp; doubtfully in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of religion to faſten vpon a reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is now. It concerneth our freehold to embrace the religion, which by the gracious benefit of her Maieſties lawes hath beene now ſo many yeeres and is ſtill (and that excluſiuely) afforded and authorized vnto vs. It is euen this time
<pb facs="tcp:5724:12"/>into which we are fallen, in which our tractablenes and our allurablenes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and godlines is inſtantly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Let vs not be halfe <hi>Iapheths</hi> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> was at the hearing of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 26.28.</note> but whole <hi>Iapheths:</hi> let vs be fully and confirmedly wonne to this true and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religion, which the Lord hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed vs ſo long. When men are loſt this way, they are loſt to God, and they are loſt to their prince: there is not a Papiſt made, but Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> loſeth a ſubiect.</p>
            <p>But ſhall we conſider the reaſon of this ſelling vp to error? it may appeare in the former example before the floud: where the Sethites were ſeduced by the carnall entiſements of the Cainites, by their men, who as may appeare Gen. 4. were men of parts; and by their women, who as may appeare Gen. 6. were beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull. Voluptuouſnes then is the witch, for looke how a gorged and ſurfetted ſtomach maketh an il aking head by the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:12"/>vapors aſcending, as appeareth by drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards (who will rue their gorge if they repent not) ſo a voluptuous heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the iudgement, and ſmokes out the eye of the vnderſtanding. Poperie hath no new arguments but the olde col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts in a new diſh, but infatuate fleſh wormes cannot iudge of falſe dice: they haue drunke of the whores wine, and haue loſt their wits.</p>
            <p>But alas how many are there which anſwer to the name of <hi>Iapheth,</hi> as <hi>Abſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> anſwered to the name of <hi>Abſhalom</hi> (which ſignifieth the fathers peace) which bring as much tractablenes to the Church as he brought peace and comfort to his father? <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> when they gaue thoſe names, ſpake as they would haue it: but the wicked will do as they luſt.</p>
            <p>Yet the lord hath ſaid enough to melt the obſtinate though they were rocks, <hi>becauſe he knoweth that they are obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 48.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and their necke is an yron ſinew and
<pb facs="tcp:5724:13"/>their brow braſſe.</hi> And therefore who can come after him to ſay any more? All that we can do is to repeat his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any compaſsion &amp; mercie, let vs be like minded, hauing the ſame loue, beeing of one accord and of one iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Let <hi>Iapheth</hi> come to <hi>Shem,</hi> for <hi>Shem</hi> may not come to <hi>Iapheth:</hi> no the Lord hath forbidden it by <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15.19 Iſaiah. 11.6.7</note> It is a prophecie of the fierceſt if they be not reprobates, <hi>that the Wolfe, Leoparde, Lion, and Beare ſhall be made innocent, and ſociable to the moſt harmeleſſe and helpleſſe creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond concluſion out of this text is thus framed, that becauſe the conuerſion of <hi>Iapheth</hi> is determined to be by the onely power of God, it is therefore required of neceſſitie that the Lord himſelfe by his ſpirit performe it. <hi>The Lord</hi> (who onely can) <hi>ſhall entiſe Iapheth.</hi> For although this text doth
<pb facs="tcp:5724:13"/>expreſly containe neither the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of neceſſitie, that it muſt needes bee the Lord that muſt doe it; nor the excluſiue that none other can do it: yet vnder this zealous contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Gods mercy and power in this affectionate ſpeech <hi>The Lord,</hi> it hath them both by implication, by preſuppoſing that ſeeing the Lord will needes haue it done, hee muſt need doe it himſelfe, becauſe none others can. If anie doe ſtill obiect that this point that it is Gods onely work to conuert, cannot bee concluded out of this Text without adding the word <hi>onely</hi> vnto it, let him againe vnderſtand that it is not added preſumptuouſly but only in ſenſe ſupplied, where otherwiſe it is vnderſtood &amp; meant alreadie. And this ſupply is after the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Chriſts collection out of thoſe words of <hi>Moſes, that we muſt ſerue God,</hi> from whence he gathereth that we muſt ſerue god alone:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.13. Math. 4.10.</note> teaching vs to conclude in like caſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:5724:14"/>if the ſcriptures doe ſhew that there is not any other power of conuerſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſpirit of God (as we ſhall ſee they doe) then where it is ſaid that the Lord conuerteth, it is there meant that he onely conuerteth and none other. So then this text teacheth vs that true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion is not the worke of any inferior power, but is one of the peculiar works of the holy &amp; omnipotent ſpirit of God. And if the queſtion ſhould be to whom it did appertaine to preuaile by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, would we not haue recourſe and refuge to this ſcripture for ſolution, <hi>The Lord ſhall perſwade Iapheth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This likewiſe appeareth vnto vs by the euidence of other ſcriptures. Firſt, the excluſiue is plaine,<note place="margin">1. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> 
               <hi>that he that plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth is not anie thing at all,</hi> that is to ſay, in the worke of true conuerſion.</p>
            <p>And the neceſſity is as plaine where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come to me except the father which hath ſent me draw him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.44.</note> he himſelfe muſt of neceſſitie draw him.
<pb facs="tcp:5724:14"/>For this is true of <hi>euerie perfect gift that it commeth downe from the father of lights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I am. 1.17.</note> and he reſerueth the donation to himſelfe. And therefore the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Lord thou haſt wrought all our works for vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 26.12</note> The ſcriptures before the Lord reuiueth vs, call <hi>vs dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>yea dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes.</hi> And the ſonne of God ſaith, <hi>that our reuiuing from this death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 5.25.</note> 
               <hi>muſt be by hearing the voice of the ſonne of God.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that our quickning (meaning this firſt quickning) muſt be by no leſſe then <hi>by the ſpirit of him that raiſed vp Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.11.</note> And he likewiſe otherwhere aſcribeth faith <hi>to the working of Gods mightie power.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.19.</note> So that if there follow eyther will or deed in vs, <hi>God worketh that alſo of his good pleaſure and will.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> As <hi>Fulgentius</hi> more largely expreſſeth it:<note place="margin">Fulgen. lib. 1 ad Monimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>Dei eſt vt &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num facere velimus, &amp; vt bonum facere valeamus:</hi> Our will and our power of doing well are both to be aſcribed to God. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quos ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus
<pb facs="tcp:5724:15"/>ſanctus intus non docet indoctirede unt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt in Epoſt. Ichan. tract. 3.</note> whom the holy ghoſt teacheth not inwardly they depart vnlearned.</p>
            <p>There are two principall cauſes why we ſhould lay this to heart. The firſt, that we may not erre in the truth of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in aſcribing any thing to our ſelues, as if we were able to ſtirre vp our ſelues. For as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelues ſo much as to think any thing as of our ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>but our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fciencie is of God.</hi> And perpetuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience reuealeth it, that they which continue in this opinion of free will are egregious inueterate hypocrites, dying eyther deſperate or ſenſeleſſe.</p>
            <p>The other cauſe is, leaſt we ſhould erre in the truth of affection, that is to ſay, in thinking that a leſſer meaſure of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil ſerue in applying our ſelues to our conuerſion then will. For when we heare tell that (what other power ſoeuer of the keyes is in the Church) Chriſt himſelf carieth that <hi>key of Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rauel. 3.7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5724:15"/>
               <hi>that ſhutteth and no man can open,</hi> it will make vs to lift vp our hearts aboue all that is called the world. And certainely the Spirit of God himſelfe by this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditation lifteth vs vp to ſuch a zealouſneſſe in prayer, and ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Spirit in making towards God in all kind of duties, as they that are informed that none can conuert vs ſo as we ſhall be conuerted, that is, ſo as our conuerſion ſhall ſtand good, but only he. We may be well aſſured, that the Spirit of God worketh not effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in vs if our affections be cold in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto him: And therefore we had need to ariſe &amp; make toward him. Men pride themſelues in a few remorsfull thoughts, &amp; break y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> back of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with wilful wickednes; they offer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to their own hypocriſie, &amp; think highly of themſelues for a thing of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>Wee had more neede to diuide our prayers, and one while to ſupplicate
<pb facs="tcp:5724:16"/>ſeriouſly vnto him for ſtronger affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and another while to deſire him to bleſſe thoſe affections which hee hath beſtowed vpon vs with diuine incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, that we may feele the finger of God to worke powerfully within vs. For beſides the ſecret ſinnes of prayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes, and a kind of indeuotion tending to Atheiſme which wee commit this way, our verie outward endeuor at pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayer and at the hearing of the word is ſo prophane, and ſo ſleight, as teſtifieth to our faces that we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten our ſelues, and ſeeme to thinke that ſome leſſer power will ſerue the turne to allure vs, then the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For if we were otherwiſe minded in the truth of our hearts, we wold moſt certainely inforce our ſelues to be holy as he is holy.</p>
            <p>In the day of our viſitation when our conſcience will ſtand vpon ſtrict tearms with vs, whether we be indeed conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or no, our copper conuerſion will
<pb facs="tcp:5724:16"/>not go for currant. And when it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected vnto vs how impoſſible it is for vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert our ſelues, or for any creature to conuert vs: nay whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is detected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs what counterfeit conuerting there is in this world, wherin lightly the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted are vnconuerted; then wee will hold vp our hands to this truth (take heede leaſt too late) Then we will crie, <hi>Conuert Thou vs O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo ſhall wee be conuerted indeed.</hi> Then diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will ſeize vpon vs in an vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, and our ſure foundation will be to lay when <hi>the raine falleth, and the flouds come, and the windes blow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7.26.27.</note> A great part of men when they fall ſicke of their laſt ſickeneſſe, are like them which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues to the raging ſeas in a riuen ſhip. Their religion &amp; their faith is not the ſtrong operation of the Lord within them, but a bare conceit of faith &amp; a conceit of religion. And many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours are like freſh-water ſouldiers which brawle in Tauernes, and make
<pb facs="tcp:5724:17"/>frayes in Smithfield, before they com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to true employment; but after in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon do ſhew neither courage nor hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Much talking there is &amp; much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of religious matters: but let vs take heed that our courage faile vs not then, when we muſt either ſtand faſt or ſticke faſt. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord haue wrought effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually in vs, hee hath wrought it by the power of his might, &amp; we haue the ſenſe of his omnipotence in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quering thoſe temptations, which none but the Spirit of God could haue conquered. And if we find not this worke, let vs not driue off til night: for we will find it a long march for ſuch a darke, and durtie and tempeſtuous night. Let vs crie ſtrongly to the Lord to giue vs his Spirit, and let vs beſeech him to inlighten vs that we may diſcerne betweene our owne spirit and his Spirit. For although there be a ſpirit in man, yet it is the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almightie,<note place="margin">Iob. 32.3.</note> it is the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almightie only that giueth
<pb facs="tcp:5724:17"/>vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.8.</note> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion belongeth to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I demaund of thee, art thou conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Thy anſwer likely will be that thou truſteſt ſo. Let me aske thee againe, haſt thou felt the combate betwixt the fleſh and the Spirit within thee? It is likely that to this alſo thou wilt anſwer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely. For hee that feeleth not ſo much in caſe is of a palpable outcaſt. But giue mee leaue to aske of thee a third queſtion: Did deſt thou feele com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in that combate by the victorie of the Spirit ouer the fleſh? If thou doeſt, thou doeſt certainly acknowledge the truth of this point by experience that God himſelfe was the man of warre, and that it was the Sonne of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that by his Spirit deſtroyed the power of darkneſſe within thee. Thou canſt remember manie a ſecret and deepe ſigh, manie a feruent prayer. For it is moſt certain, that howſoeuer hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites doe abuſe theſe things, yet they
<pb facs="tcp:5724:18"/>are the muſicke of this warre: this warre I ſay wherein the holy Ghoſt ſtriketh the ſtroke, and doth all our things for vs. The free will which man hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall grace, extendeth no further then ciuill moralities or fruſtrate deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which yet hypocrites; not being able to wade out of hell, make account of, according to the prouerb, as if there were no other heauen. But the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will of a true Chriſtian is another kinde of thing, it is to partake in the diuine nature, the diuinitie of true Chriſtians is not after the vulgar ſenſe of dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, but there is beſides another maner of diuinitie of preaching, a diuinitie of hearing, a diuinitie of praying, euen to feele the diuine finger of God working in vs in theſe exerciſes; without which the breath is but ſcattered into the aire. This kind of diuinitie is the life of God in a man; &amp; it is the loweſt degree of grace that can be named, if a man haue no true ſenſe thereof, to bewaile his
<pb facs="tcp:5724:18"/>ſenſleſneſſe. It is certaine that he which is not ſtirred inwardly with religion as with a miraculous operatiue, hath not the bowels of the child of God within him. Coldneſſe is a curſe; and to make no conſcience of coldneſſe, is to haue Gods curſe vnder ſeale.</p>
            <p>This is indeed the freewill that wee profeſſe, when God giueth vs free harts to ſet manfully vpon, our corruptions, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> faith. <hi>Liberum arbitrium non euacuatur per gratiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de ſpiritu &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera. cap. 30.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ſtatuitur quia gratia ſanat voluntatem:</hi> Freewill is not auoided by grace but eſtabliſhed, becauſe grace healeth the will, that is, giueth vs a will to righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>I do the rather inſiſt vpon this point, leaſt any man ſhould deceiue his owne heart, in thinking that conuerſion is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an eaſie matter, or of eaſie meanes, Good brethren for your liues think nor ſuch a thought, but remember that if <hi>Iapheth</hi> be to be allured, the Lord muſt allure him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:19"/>
            <p>The fall of man as it can be relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by no mercie but the mercie of God: ſo neither can it be relieued by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny power but the power of God. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the meanes is great preſumption, for <hi>the Goſpell is the power of ſaluation,</hi> that is, the holy Ghoſt exerciſeth his power by it. But to aſcribe to the means that that is due to the Lord, muſt be far from vs.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay vnto me that if the Goſpell be but the inſtrument, and the power be the Lords; then all this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of preachers to deliuer the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell powerfully is needleſſe, becauſe the power is elſe where.</p>
            <p>But marke the anſwer, that the power of God is not reſerued within God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the word, but God is in the ſpirit of the Preacher to deliuer the word,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.8.</note> as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith the holie Ghoſt wrought in <hi>Peter</hi> and him towards their ſeuerall hearers, and is in the Spirit of the hearer to receiue the word. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:5724:19"/>the <hi>hearers ſhall fall on their faces and ſay, of a truth God is in you indeed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.25.</note> And therefore brethren, though ye trie the ſpirits, which ſpare not to do by the Scriptures, let them not paſſe away vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tried though they ſeeme neuer ſo ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; yet reiect not the ſpirits of the zealous becauſe they are zealous. For as there is a doctrine that is of God: ſo there are ſpirits that are of God, in whom the holy Ghoſt worketh migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily. Now if thou ſay to me, that then it will follow, that where the preaching hath no good effect, there the Preacher ſpake not from the Spirit of God: Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand for anſwer, that no ſuch thing will follow. For the holy Ghoſt may worke in a man, and yet not worke by him vpon others, but his prayer and his preaching may returne into his owne boſome. And <hi>Noahs</hi> meaning in this prophecie was, that the conuerſion of the Gentiles ſhold be wrought through the holy Ghoſt by the perſwaſiue ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:5724:20"/>of the teachers, and the perſwaſible ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the hearers. The Lord therefore increaſe among you men of a gracious perſwaſion, that may confirme you with the confirmations of God in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of God. And the Lord reueale his arme ſo in the miniſterie, that wee may haue occaſion to aſcend into that ſame ſpeech of Saint <hi>Paule, O the deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the riches of God,</hi> wherein <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith is contained the ſolution of that queſtion,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſpiritu &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera. cap. 34.</note> why ſome are conuerted rather then ſome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third concluſion out of this text is concerning the meanes which the Lord vſeth in drawing men to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to wit, that becauſe hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them, therefore hee will conuert them by allurements, <hi>The Lord ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure Iapheth,</hi> ſignifying that the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are in the doctrine of the Goſpell and in Euangelicall exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. For although wee reade how that the Lord hath laid violent hands vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5724:20"/>ſome as vpon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the way to Damaſcus,<note place="margin">Act, 9.</note> yet we muſt make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between his conſternation which tended to his conuerſion, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion it ſelfe, which was wrought when <hi>Ananias</hi> came with the word of comfort in his mouth. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that our word ought not to ſtand in <hi>the entiſing ſpeech of mans wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4.</note> for the allurements are ſpirituall. But in the meane while they are allurements ſtill. For as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord leadeth vs with the cords of a man, euen with the bands of loue, and is to vs as hee that taketh off the yoke from our iawes, and layeth meate vnto vs.</hi> How kindly alluring his Church to let him in is Chriſt induced by <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Open vnto me my ſiſter, my loue, my doue, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How amiably doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> quite himſelfe in his embaſſage,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20</note> 
               <hi>We are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Embaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you through vs, wee pray you in Chriſts ſteede that you would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled
<pb facs="tcp:5724:21"/>to God.</hi> It doth then appeare that the true doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt is alluring doctrine, and repleniſhed with ſweete inducements.</p>
            <p>But here (likely) ſome man bethin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him vpon occaſion of this ſpeech of allurement, that it is then a courſe to be taken with the Papiſts, that they might heare of this alluring attractiue. But as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith in a matter not much vnlike,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.18</note> 
               <hi>I demand, haue they not heard?</hi> Haue they not beene mercifully dealt with by her Maieſtie, and louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreated by their brethren? <hi>The Lord be iudge betweene them and vs concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this thing.</hi> Whatſoeuer good courſe hath yet beene vnaſſayed which tendeth to their allurement, the Lord direct the hearts of his fathfull ſeruants to take it. Alwayes prouided that their lenitie be not abuſed, <hi>and that fooliſh pity marre not the citie.</hi> I cannot come after with any ſupply of new allurements: but I doe onely repeate theſe two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.
<pb facs="tcp:5724:21"/>The firſt, that the Papiſts of this land which are aforehand brought and ſold like ſheepe by their falſe brethren the Papiſts beyond ſea, ſhall eſcape the Butcher by running from the Drouer.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, that they ſhall returne to a God which will in holy mercie do that to them which a man may not doe for his wife, if when he hath put her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for her lewdnes for a time to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble her ſhe diſdaine him, and become a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans. <hi>Shall he returne vnto her? ſhould not then this land be polluted? But they haue played the harlot with manie lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, yet turn again to me, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs come to the point. It is confeſſed on both ſides both by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, and by vs, that the Goſpell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureth. But in the meane while the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie is growne on which ſide this alluring doctrine may be, on their ſide or on ours. It ſhal be therefore very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent both to the text and time (if your attention will reuiue it ſelfe) to diſcuſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5724:22"/>this point, though not in ſuch meaſure as it may indeede be diſcuſſed, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of the gift of God.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts haue alreadie furniſhed out maine confident allegations that their religion is moſt politicall, going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by a long induction to conclude, that it ſorteth beſt with the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the common wealth. In which diſputation, as they do often goe beyond the profeſſion of diuinitie: ſo euen there where they keepe beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, their diuinity is turned into huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. For their verie arguments doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token but an earthly well being (if they could haue hit that) and they manifeſt themſelues to haue forgotten that life is of the duall number. In this point like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are verie out-bearing, and the ſucceſſe which they haue found in their allurements hath made them arrogant enticers. For they are indeede though verie ſcorpions, yet ſuch (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5724:22"/>ſaith) <hi>whoſe faces are like the faces of men and they haue haire as the haire of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 9.7.8</note> And to confeſſe the truth, what affliction ſoeuer they pretend to haue beene impoſed vpon them: yet they haue enioyed ſo much peace and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, that they haue thriuen by it in eloquence, and in the muſicke of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids, euen like the Naphthalites with eaſe and proſperitie they haue learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o giue goodly words.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.21.</note> But the queſtion betweene them and vs is not who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he cunninger enticers, or the better painters they or we, but whoſe doctrin hath more reaſon to allure the child of God, theirs or ours.</p>
            <p>As let the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion firſt be, whether a man being <hi>compos mentis</hi> (as we ſay) wil rather be allured to Gods free grace which the Spirit of truth teacheth by vs but of Gods holy word, or to his owne merites, which the ſpirit of errour tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth by them out of their own braine.</p>
            <p>They ſay that we ſell Paradiſe good
<pb facs="tcp:5724:23"/>cheape, becauſe we hold it at the Lords expreſſe rate, as it ſtandeth in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> where we are called to buy indeed, but to pay nothing, hauing nothing to pay (as he ſaith.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 55.1.</note>) And we ſay that they ſell hell verie deere, when they make men to pay their merits for it, which otherwiſe coſt-free, that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that blaſphemous arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, ſhould haue it ouer ſoone, for their impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of dead works. What man that is not bewitched out of the wit of a man, will forſake the doctrine of truſting in Gods free grace, but once to leane to truſt to himſelfe? Wee in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Supper doe offer Chriſt ſpritually to the faithful receiuer. They offer him carnally, that is, monſtrouſly and irkſomelie, and that to the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. On which ſide is the better allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? They offer the pardons of men, wee offer the pardon of God to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. They require bodily penance for ſins, and put in contrition for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:5724:23"/>ſake. We require ſpirituall as the acceptable ſacrifice, and value bodily exerciſe at a lowe rate. We teach that the preaching of the worde muſt bee heard, which pierceth and entreth into the ſoule. They teach that maſſe muſt be heard which biteth not: for this is the hypocrits comfort, <hi>miſſa non mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det.</hi> As for their preaching, it is the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a Drone without a ſting, except they be diſpoſed to playe the Terma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants againſt the truth. We teach that a mans purgatorie conſiſteth in reſpect of merit in Chriſts death, and in reſpect of ſpirit in the mortification of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions whiles we liue here, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of Chriſts death. They teach, that if the Prieſts be not be better paid, a man muſt abide in purgatorie long after his death. Let as many as are not ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the diuels miſts ſee with their eies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea let them feele with their hands, which of theſe doctrines are more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be true. But let vs to it againe.
<pb facs="tcp:5724:24"/>They ſay that prieſtes may not marrie with a good conſcience. And we ſay that all thoſe of them which cannot liue continently, are bound in conſcience to marrie. Their reaſon is, an vnlawfull vow. Our reaſon is, that they, their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and their preachings may not bee polluted with damnable hypocriſie, by reaſon of their wilfull pollutions. They alleadge that we teach voluptuouſneſſe, when we teach thus the auoiding of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. But we alleadge that they by conſequence teach ſtolen voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which burneth and waſteth the conſcience: for thus to frequent relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, is to cauterize the ſpirit and <hi>vaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conſcientiam,</hi> as the ſchoolemen aptly tearme it. Are there any but bewailed wretches that cannot ſee on which ſide the truth ſtandeth? Their doctrine is, that it is preſumption by any meanes to be rid of the feare of damnation ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily. Our doctrine is, that whoſoeuer loueth the Lord out of a pure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:5724:24"/>that is, out of a conſcience inlightened by Gods word, and not offended by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in ſinne againſt the conſcience ſo inlightened, may iuſtly vpon that grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d receiue from the holy ghoſt aſſurance of his ſaluation, though the Fathers of Trent condemne this perſwaſion neuer ſo much. They affirme that a man hath free will to do things truely good, which is a deuiſe of the deuill to teach men to preſume of that they haue not, that they might erre vnto perdition. We teach that a man hath no free will in his nature to doe any true ſanctified and ſpirituall good, that men acknowledging their bondage may ſeeke free will of God.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, concerning the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (whereby all muſt be tried) they teach that the vulgar tranſlation which is ſo groſly faultie, is onely authenticall. Wee teach that the originall text in Hebrewe and Greeke is onely authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</p>
            <p>Theſe differences are ſo manifeſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:5724:25"/>theſe faces are of ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie hue, that it is no maruell if the holy ghoſt ſay, that men muſt be firſt drunke before they can be deceiued in them.<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.8. &amp; 17.2.</note> Otherwiſe their deluſions are as eaſie to diſcerne, as that <hi>Iezabel</hi> had borrowed her face then ſhe looked out at the window. The whore of Babylon is highly mounted, finely painted, and terribly armed, and theſe be her allurements. The doctrine of the goſpell hath beautie in it ſelfe, inward comfort, and conſtant colour, and theſe are her allurements.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture ſome man will ſay vnto me, I pray you what allurement is in your doctrine of mortification which you ſo much vrge?</p>
            <p>And which you extend ſo far; that a man can haue no peace in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that fauoureth and retaineth any ſinne in himſelfe againſt his conſcience? Which determineth that a man is in a damnable caſe whatſoeuer good deedes ſeeme to be in him, if he yeelde not to
<pb facs="tcp:5724:25"/>the worke of the holy ghoſt for a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but of any one knowne ſinne which fighteth againſt the peace of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Dearely beloued, I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt to take this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, caſt it into the balance and marke well the ſcales.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe in deed to begin withal, that this doctrine fawneth not vpon hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, but remooueth them to their wo, and the weale of the Church. But why is it? is it not becauſe they are hypocrits? To the reſt may it not be truely ſaid of this doctrine,<note place="margin">Matt. 11, 29 30.</note> that it is <hi>an eaſie yoke and a light burden?</hi> Is it not an alluring doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine that hath but one onely difficultie, and is otherwiſe accompanied with moſt certaine conſolation? The difficultie is to ſhake off the vnconſcionable ſin that cleaueth ſo faſt to vs, and tarrieth behind to miſchiefe vs. Were it not damnable doctrine to diſpenſe with that which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth no diſpenſation? ſhould we take vpon vs to heale with ſweete wordes like
<pb facs="tcp:5724:26"/>witches? Be ſtrong in the Lord, and of a good courage in throwing away that ſin, and then the maine brunt is ouer and the worſt is paſt. Holde thee there, and thou maieſt enioy perpetuall, that is, vndiſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued conſolations notwithſtanding a thouſand infirmities. For ſo long as the power of mortification deſtroyeth thy ſinfull affections as they riſe, and ſo long as thou art vnfainedly diſpleaſed with all ſinne, and doeſt <hi>mortifie the deedes of the body by the ſpirit,</hi> thy caſe is the caſe of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And when thou art once ſoundly confirmed in this reſolution, thou art not onely in the caſe, but alſo in the ſtate of ſaluation, thou ſhalt liue &amp; not die. What would a man haue more then this? But the Papiſtes haue found an eaſe for this matter. For they which accuſe the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the goſpell to be a doctrine of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, becauſe of the article of iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by faith only, do themſelues by indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, by pardons, by merits of Saints, and by ſetting of good deedes againſt ill,
<pb facs="tcp:5724:26"/>teach fooliſh virgins that oyle is to bee begged or bought, wherby they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into a damnable ſleepe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie.</p>
            <p>It would allure a pyrate indeede to be of their religion, if he might be ſure to buy out his puniſhment after his death with the robberies and rapines of his life. In the meane time ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as this, hath brought Atheiſme into the world, and that alſo of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt kind. For a Popiſh Atheiſt is an hideous mungrell, euen a verie Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taure. As to ſay the very truth, Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Atheiſme are very coincident, and their differences very obſcure. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie is a ſenſuall diſſembling with Gods, &amp; Atheiſme is a ſenſual mocking of God. The Papiſt is a make-god, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Atheiſt is a mock-god. And you may be ſure, that the maker wilbe ſo bold as to be a mocker in time. The Papiſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludeth his conſcience, and the Atheiſt derideth his conſcience. Poperie (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:5724:27"/>
               <hi>copia cornu</hi> of ſenſuall ceremonies, for euerie ſenſe a play-fellow, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie religion, the good-fellowes religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) comforteth the fleſh, &amp; Atheiſme ſuppreſſeth the ſpirit. Brethren, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it well, and you ſhall find that Poperie to them that haue heard the Goſpell ſoundly and ſincerely taught, marke well what I ſay, to them that haue heard the Goſpell ſoundly and ſincerely taught, hath nothing in it to allure anie but hypocrites, nor anie thing in it to detaine anie ſuch in that religion, but thoſe which are in a faire forwardneſſe to degenerate into A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture it will be alleaged that there are manie euen in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Realme, that after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Goſpell are drawne away in their verie conſciences to Poperie. But I aske who are they? Are they not they of whom a man may ſay, <hi>O how great is that darkeneſſe when their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5724:27"/>
               <hi>light is become darkeneſſe?</hi> when the candle of their conſcience is put out? Are they not they which are giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to a forlorne ſenſe? <hi>whoſe thoughts and conſcience</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle worth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10, 20</note> becauſe (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) themſelues being defiled Infidels <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is pure to them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>but euen their mindes and conſciences are defiled.</hi> It is no great matter which way the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of theſe men doe wagge. I will tell you (dearely beloued) what may be obſerued of many that are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly reconciled Papiſts in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that if there were no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect but the loſſe of them for the good that was in them when they were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, they are better loſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> found, and become that Synagogue better then this Church, for they ſuite it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Men of a proditorious, imperious and luxurious diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I talke of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? ſeeing that kind of religion is
<pb facs="tcp:5724:28"/>the refuge of the vnconſc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ionable: whoſe trade is firſt to promiſe what they luſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make heretikes whom they luſt, and at the laſt to breake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with them when and how they luſt. Their religion it ſelfe is ſpied well enough by many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſors of it. And there are manie that are Papiſts euen againſt their conſcience, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience were to bee ſtinted at this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; that Poperie is a falſe and fraudulent religion, <hi>haereſis Catholica impoſtura magna,</hi> the impoſture of the world. But to ſay the truth, they are not Papiſts againſt their conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue no conſcience <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſenſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore as for the examples and liues of men whereby wee are to allure one another, they neede not to boaſt ſo much as they do, conſidering that their religion conſiſteth by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the profeſſion of many great crimes. Againſt the third commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:5724:28"/>they profeſſe reſolution of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, if it ſerue their turne when they are ſworne to thoſe that they call here-tikes. Againſt the fiſt commandement they profeſſe diſobedience to their princes, if their holy father incite them to it. Againſt the ſixt commandement they profeſſe murther vpon the like warrantie. Againſt the ſeuenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement by barring mariage, and expreſſe preferring the faults of ſingle life before it, they profeſſe filthineſſe and vnchaſtitie in thoſe that ought to bee moſt pure. Againſt the eight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement they profeſſe making merchandize of ſoules. Againſt the ninth commandement vnder pretence of reconciling to the Church, they profeſſe alienation of ſubiects from their natural princes, and are the moſt renowmed artificers of miſchiefe and debate that euer were heard of. All theſe they doe directly or indirectly profeſſe beſides the reſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:29"/>
            <p>As for vs which profeſſe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it behooueth vs on the other ſide to allure by our example in better maner then we do, and not to cauſe the name of God to be blaſphemed by theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts through vs, but rather to <hi>let our light ſo ſhine before men, that they may glorifie our father which is in heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 5.16.</note> For the truth is, that wee are to too ſhort in this kind of allurement. The doctrin which we profeſſe is indeed Gods allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring doctrine, but our examples are not ſuch. The workes of the Papiſts eſpecially many of their Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an piles, are monuments of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. And our works are monuments of the prophanation of Gods truth, as our antiſabbatarie play-houſes. But who doth anie common good? The merits of an arrogant Papiſt are caried after him with a dolefull <hi>Item</hi> fit for a black <hi>Sanctus,</hi> that they will not go for payment. And our works, if we repent not, will follow after vs and giue vs our
<pb facs="tcp:5724:29"/>payment, becauſe we in our generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue not beene ſo gracious in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring, as the Papiſts haue beene wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in theirs. The Lord giue vs grace to repent.</p>
            <p>The fourth concluſion out of this text is, that all thoſe true <hi>Iapheths</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord ſhall take in hand to allure, ſhall <hi>dwell in the tents of Shem,</hi> that is, ſhall come to the true Church, and ſhall abide therein. If God be not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs in this thing, all his mercies are fruſtrate vnto vs. And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this bleſſing he after a ſort exhorteth them, to wit, to lay hold vpon it. For it is the greateſt fauour that God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon men in this world, to make them true members of his true Church. And this is the grace if wee bee not vtterly vngratious, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all worldly things we will deſire and affect, though it ſhould coſt vs all we are worth to purchaſe this field. As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>One thing haue I deſired of
<pb facs="tcp:5724:30"/>the Lord, that I will require,</hi> and will not alter this petition into another,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4 5</note> 
               <hi>that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life to behold the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Lord, and to viſit his temple.</hi> For as he ſaith.<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>Mount Sion is the ioy of the whole earth,</hi> to wit, as farre as God hath any people in the earth belonging to his election. For in it (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>he ſpeaketh forth all his glorie.</hi> This is the Arke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 29.9.</note> out of which there is no ſaluation: all elſe is a floud fifteene cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits aboue the higheſt mountaines. They therefore which cannot be allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come and dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> muſt periſh. For euen the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God themſelues are no better then wretches ſo long as they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from hence. Whoſe ſtate is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the prodigall ſonne, that was faine to feed on ſwill and ſwads.<note place="margin">Luk. 15.15, 16.</note> And <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth of his baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Church, which yet he was not guiltie of,<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.</note> 
               <hi>Wo is to me</hi> (ſaith he)
<pb facs="tcp:5724:30"/>
               <hi>that I remaine in Meſhech, and dwell in the tents of Kedar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay vnto me, that I ſhal not need to vrge this point becauſe it is alredie confeſſed. But I am conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to replie, that the confeſſion of the truth of it is not much more generall, then the diſauowing and reiecting of the practiſe. For how manie are there which hold off, and almoſt take a pride to be vnſtayed in the matter of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? How manie which by pretence of diſagreements in the Church, cannot tell what to make of themſelues?</p>
            <p>The Papiſts they haue ſought vp their gods againe, which they had caſt to the backes and to the moules, they frequent Maſſe in corners, and they behaue themſelues ſo as the Familiſts in their aſſemblies: and that company of them which are called Ieſuites, may more worthily bee called Adamites, which were the firſt founders of the Familiſts. For theſe Maſſe-monges
<pb facs="tcp:5724:31"/>watch <hi>Tammuz</hi> in the nights, and theſe night-birds keepe little better then the feaſts of <hi>Iſis</hi> &amp; <hi>Oſiris</hi> in this citie. As for the reſt, if the name of Recuſant ſhould be taken ſtrictly for euerie one that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth ſo to dwell in the tents of <hi>She<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as the Lord would take in good part, the Recuſants of this land are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. When we conſider how long the Goſpell hath continued amongſt vs, and compare it with the great heapes of people in this City which make no difference of the Sabboth day at all for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake, we may truly cry out of a prodigious wickednes. It can not be denyed but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are now more ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preachers of Gods word amongſt you, then euer there were. But the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the moſt that profeſſe, and the rudeneſſe of the troupes of thoſe that ſcorne to profeſſe is very offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and loathſome. There are they ſay belonging to diuers ſeuerall pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes many thouſand people, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb facs="tcp:5724:31"/>more to ſome then the pariſh church can contayne; though I know not the caſe, yet I propound it to you. And how do you thinke are a greate parte of this people occupied, when they ſhoulde bee preſent at the hearing of the word? I would demaund of the frowardeſt man in all this preſence, whether he do not thinke in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that the greateſt part of them are ſo frarre from being in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> that they are in the tents of <hi>Cham.</hi> For I pray you tell me, are not theſe drunken Tauernes and victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes, theſe play-houſes and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell houſes the tents of <hi>Cham,</hi> where all the reſt of their villanies are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed and made vp with the ſcoffing at <hi>Noah?</hi> Aſſuredly (dearely beloued) if that which is called co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience be any better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ieſt, &amp; that which is called Gods word be any better then a ſtale, theſe are damnable things to be done,
<pb facs="tcp:5724:32"/>and therfore horrible things to bee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe vnto you that my skil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth not duly to limit forth the blame of the rulers, to lay it iuſtly where it is. Vnfainedly I ſpeake it, I forbeare that particular courſe for no other cauſe, but becauſe I would not reproue ſinne with ſinne by ſpeaking into a matter before I know it. But well I am ſure, that if they which are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the reformotion of this abuſe by the places which they ſuſtaine, did buſie themſelues therein more zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then yet they do, they ſhould pleaſe God better then in anie thing els for the moſt part wherein they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>They that come out of the world into the Church, come out of a deſert and they that come into the Church, as moſt men are come in, come into a deſert, &amp; are like ſheep without a
<pb facs="tcp:5724:32"/>ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heard. This great forreſt of London is full of couert for wandring creatures, and there are too manie priuiledges for ſinners. I beſeech you heare me this one thing with patience, and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to weigh it well. The Magiſtrates being annoyed with the diſorders of looſe and wicked perſons which ſwarme about this citie, do performe a laudable office indeede in reuiſing the orders of Bridewell, and in vrging better execution of the good lawes which tend to a remedie. But except the tents of <hi>Shem</hi> were ſurueyed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and the apparance there were better vrged, it is to ſmall purpoſe to endeuour this externall reformation. For this one thing be ſure of, that theſe looſe perſons, theſe diſguiſed conycat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers haue informed themſelues of their ſtate what it would bee, if they ſhould change their courſe with that which the Magiſtrate would vrge, to
<pb facs="tcp:5724:33"/>wit, that it would be both more poore and more painfull. And therefore they are reſolued rather to venture the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt penaltie, then to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to this change. So that there is nothing that can effectually reclaime them but onely this, to marſhall them to the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> For there they ſhall find allurements to quiet their minds in obedience. They ſhall finde that they are not bidden to loſſe, but that they ſhall better their ſtate by the change. For to dwell rightly in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> is in ſome meaſure to dwell in heauen. And I would the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates would duly conſider, how much they are beholding to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell in this behalfe: (aſſuredly the Magiſtrates are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull if they vſe them not reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely and kindly.) And I would the Miniſters would likewiſe endeuour to bring hither their forces. For ſo ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:5724:33"/>they directly ſatisfie their owne duties in bringing men to Gods Church, and conſequently aſſiſt the Magiſtrate in the reformation of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>And as for the people themſelues which are runne wild, be they poore or rich, I would they would conſider what wrong they doe themſelues with this out-lying, &amp; what benefit it would be to them to come and dwell in theſe tents. And it were to bee wiſhed that ſome euen of thoſe which reſort to <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe and will not come at their owne Church, and when they are here delude the law with walking and talking, were better ordered: for their reſort hither is like the piller-prayers of manie which kneele downe only for faſhion ſake. I ſay, I would not onely the poore, but alſo the rich of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders would obſerue it of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſoeuer. For as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:5724:34"/>
               <hi>Quiſquis ille eſt &amp; qualiſcunque ille eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. 181. de tempore.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtianus non eſt qui in Chriſti Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia non eſt.</hi> Be what he may be, he is no Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is not in Chriſts Church: though his head were of braſſe.</p>
            <p>Pardon my libertie of ſpeech of theſe Libertines. Theſe Conycatchers and vagrant <hi>Caines,</hi> which haue gotten a perpetuitie of haunting Tauernes and infamous houſe without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of dayes, and without reſpect of the time either of prayer or preaching are no better then the diuels rogues. But if they would come to <hi>Shems</hi> tents their priu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ledges ſhould be great.</p>
            <p>For firſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2, 12.</note> wheras they are now a ſort of maiſterleſſe hounds and <hi>Atheiſts in the world</hi> (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) they ſhould be receiued into the ſeruice of God, and ſo come vnder his tuition, which would bee a rowling away of their ſhame: for this non apparance is a ſhamefull crime of irkeſome reproch.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:34"/>
            <p>Secondly, by being in checke-roll in his tents they ſhould be capable of the benefite of his ſeruants, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the grace of the holy Ghoſt. For theſe wild men, theſe Faunes and Satyrs (as I may ſay) are a kind of demo niacks, and are not ſo much as capable of the Spirit of God, til they haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues to bee members of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, by tarying their turne they ſhould be not only capable, but it <hi>ſhold euen be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to their faith.</hi> And there would be a maruellous change worthy to be celebrated with a ſong of Angels. Wheras now they are ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred with the horrors of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſo that the ſound of fear is euer in their eares. Againſt this Satan ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not otherwiſe ſuccour them, then by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to make out a power of blaſphemies and deriſions both of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and hell, or to earth themſelues in
<pb facs="tcp:5724:35"/>the caues of obliuion, that the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come may not come into their mindes. Then they ſhould be able to pacifie their conſciences with ſound arguments of their ſaluation: and the grace of God would perſwade their conſciences to take part on their ſide. And when their heart was become their friend, it would perſwade their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to dine and ſup with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Which would be a royall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to the poorer ſort for the hard fare they ſhould find in the world by changing their courſe, and a diſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all their dainties to the rich.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:5724:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>This ſecond part was not vttered for lacke of time, but was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by authoritie thought fit to be annexed in the print.</head>
               <p>NOw followeth the ſecond parte of the text of <hi>Iapheths</hi> participating with <hi>Shem,</hi> or rather his ſucceeding of <hi>Shem</hi> in dominion ouer <hi>Canaan; And Canaan ſhall be their ſeruant,</hi> that is, let <hi>Iapheth</hi> continue in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> and then he ſhall hold <hi>Canaan</hi> in ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. For the ſeruitude of <hi>Canaan</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Iapheth,</hi> is annexed to <hi>Iapheths</hi> dwelling in the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> And ſo groweth the fift concluſion out of this text, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that the ſubduing of ours and Gods enemies, is a benefit tyed to our conſtancy in true religion. It is cleare enough, that they which are helde in ſeruitude being of <hi>Canaans</hi> broode, doe foſter diſdaine and enmity. But in the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:36"/>meane while as Salomon ſayeth, <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 16.7.</note> 
                  <hi>his enemies ſhal bee contented to bee at peace with him.</hi> Therefore the Pſalmiſt ſayeth, <hi>O that my people had harkened vnto me, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael had walked in my wayes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.13.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>I would ſoone haue humbled their enemies, and turned my hand againſt their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The haters of the Lord ſhould haue beene ſubiect vnto him, though fainedly, and their time of ruling ſhould haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for euer.</hi> On the other ſide the ſcripture ſayeth,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.43.44.</note> 
                  <hi>That when wee ceaſe to walke in the wayes of the Lord</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a principal part is to vphold his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) <hi>our enemies ſhall bee the head, and wee ſhalbe the tayle.</hi> And ſuch likewiſe are the examples of the word. When <hi>Eli</hi> ſuffered Gods ſeruice to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his ſonnes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Sam. 2.30.32.</note> the Lord remooued him (you know howe) and ſaide vnto him, <hi>Them that honour me will I honor, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhalbe deſpiſed.</hi> And further he ſayeth to him, <hi>And
<pb facs="tcp:5724:36"/>thou ſhalt ſee anguiſh in the habitation of the Lord, in ſtead of al thoſe things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God would haue bleſſed Iſrael.</hi> And of the children of Iſrael the ſcripture ſayeth,<note place="margin">Iudg. 2 13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>They for ſooke the Lord and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Baal and Aſhtaroth, and the wrath of the Lord was hotte againſt Iſrael. And he deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the hands of ſpoilers and ſolde them into the handes of their enemies round about them, ſo that they could no longer ſtand before their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> So we read of Salomon,<note place="margin">1. King. 11.14.23.26.</note> how he went to wreck when he had once yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the corruption of religion, at the inſtigation of his wiues: The Lord ſtirred vp enemie vpon enemie againſt him, euen thoſe which before ſerued him. In the recitall of theſe ſcriptures, we haue neede to make vſe of two wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſayings of S. Paul. The firſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4</note> 
                  <hi>That Whatſoeuer things are written, are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning,</hi> to comfort and animate vs to holde our religion. The ſecond, that theſe examples of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:5724:37"/>vengeance on them that forſooke it, are enſamples to vs to terrifie vs from once meditating of ſuch a ſinne.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.6</note> Let it not come into our mindes, that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſedome in yeelding any thing from the truth of God. Let vs not think that others will thinke that wee deale wiſely if wee take that courſe. For the ſcripture affirmeth that our ſtrict hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our religion is our wiſedome,<note place="margin">Deut. 4, 6.</note> and our vnderſtanding in the ſight of the people.</p>
               <p>Great is the praiſe of Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, for holding her owne, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods owne in this behalfe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we conſider how ſhe hath beene vrged. The lawes which haue beene made for the repreſſing of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are all ſtill in force, and we doe yet abide in the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi> And aſſure your ſelues brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoughts of God are tender towardes vs, if wee will ſerue him; ſo the thoughtes of Queene Elizabeth his ſeruant and
<pb facs="tcp:5724:37"/>daughter, our Queene and mother, are tender towardes vs in this matter of preſeruation of religion. If we will be quietly zealous and charitably tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we ſhall ſee, that as her entrance was graced with the reſtoring; ſo her proceeding ſhalbe honoured with the conſtant conſeruing of religion. So long as weekeepe vs within the limits of wiſe zeale, and deſcend not to the heady courſes of the vaſt vulgar, but do maintaine the true ſeruice of God, as followers and not forerunners of wiſe gouernment, not preuenting it by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe; wee ſhalbe able to keepe theſe <hi>Canaanites</hi> in ſubiection, though they did exceede vs in number neuer ſo much.</p>
               <p>If any ſay that our holding religion will not holde downe our enemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the moſt religious at ſome times are oppreſſed. I anſwere, that martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is but in particular places, or of particular perſons. But the like cannot
<pb facs="tcp:5724:38"/>be made to appeare of a whole land by any ſtory. It <hi>Iapheth</hi> dwell in <hi>Shems</hi> tents, <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhall ſurely ſerue him. The word of God ought to ſuffice to confirme vs in the truth of this point. But let vs wade into the matter by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe reaſon (as they ſay) impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it, ſeeing the Papiſts are ſo many.</p>
               <p>Our entrance into the firſt reaſon is out of an vſuall ſaying that wee haue amongſt vs, that one true man is too hard for two theeues by reaſon of his confidence. This certainly is moſt true in the matter of religion, that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence giueth courage. This is an only grace to daunt theſe theeniſh <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.7.</note> as the Lord ſaid to Ioſhua, <hi>Onely be thou ſtrong, and of a moſt valiant cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</hi> According to the promiſe in the Law,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.7.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſhall cauſe thine enemies that riſe againſt thee to fall before thy face.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh. 23.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall come out againſt thee one way, and ſhall flee before thee ſeuen waies.</hi> And againe, <hi>one of you ſhall chaſe a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb facs="tcp:5724:38"/>of them.</hi> And we may be ſure that if the ſpeech of the men of Iudah (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fewer) was fiercer then the ſpeech of the men of Iſrael (being more) by reaſon of their ſpirite,<note place="margin">2. Sa, 19.43</note> that then much more the ſpirite of one true Chriſtian, will ouer-match the ſpirit of many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. And ſo we haue the ſentence of S. Luke (a man of God for his obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) in the ſtory of S. Stephen, <hi>But they were not able to reſiſt the wiſedome and the Spirit by which hee ſpake.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> This reaſon is fortified further by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of our aduerſaries perſon. For as the matter now ſtandeth, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious Papiſt is a double theefe, both in the cauſe of religion, and alſo in the queſtion of lawe and obedience to the Prince: and therfore falſe hearted. And certainly if they be duly ſtood to, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by thoſe to whom it doth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, they will take their heeles. And marke what I ſay to you, the magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity of our moſt excellent Prince
<pb facs="tcp:5724:39"/>may put mettall into vs. And this is the firſt reaſon.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is taken from the protection of God ouer his Church. For although the flocke of Chriſt were leſſe, and this herd of goates were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo numbrous: yet if the ſheepe wil cleaue to their ſhepheard, the Lorde hath promiſed to create vpon euery place of mount Zion,<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 4, 5.</note> and vpon the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies thereof a cloud and a ſmoke by day, and the ſhining of a flaming fire by night. For vpon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</p>
               <p>This protection of God by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of reaſon may bee thus manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vnto vs. Conſider the protection of God ouer the politicall ſtate of the world, I meane ſuſtaining the ſtate of common wealthes, wherby euery man hath the benefit of enioying his owne. There is no man well aduiſed that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth this ſecurity wholy to ciuil go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment. For we ſee that if the people
<pb facs="tcp:5724:39"/>were numbred by the pole and due no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taken of euerie mans diſpoſition, that there are three to one which had rather liue of the ſpoile, and thoſe alſo couragious and valiant vnthrifts. And in other particular Cities and townes where it is more eaſie to take a true ſuruey then in this, it is an apparant caſe that there are enow penurious and idle male-contents euerie night couching, to expell all the ſubſtantiall inhabitants of the towne out of their houſes before morning. For the well &amp; ciuilly diſpoſed in a common wealth are but an handfull to thoſe that are ſtroy-goods and of ill behauiour. And yet ye ſee what the Lord doth for the protection of the ciuill conuerſation of men. And will ye not beleeue that his protection will be greater ouer his Church? Certainly he that checketh the ſea with the tender ſand,<note place="margin">Iere. 5.22. Pſal. 104.22.23.</note> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>the wilde beaſts of the forreſt tore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre to their dennes</hi> when man goeth to
<pb facs="tcp:5724:40"/>his labour will deliuer vs from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our ſoules, though they were double as many, and compell them to ſerue vs, if we will ſerue the Lord.</p>
               <p>But peraduenture thou wilt ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that it ſufficeth vs to holde our owne, though wee ſtande not vpon tearmes of keeping others in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Conſider diligently what muſt be anſwered, that Papiſts are not to bee helde in ſubiection vnder vs as they are men, but as they are Papiſts; not in reſpect of their perſon, but in reſpect of their religion. In which regard we are bound to hold them vnder in Gods behalfe. For who are wee, that wee ſhould preſume to depart with Gods right? If the Lord haue truſted vs, and we let them go, how ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape that ſentence that our life ſhall <hi>go for theirs?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 20.39.</note> And thinke with your ſelues, that if <hi>Aſa</hi> thought it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to put downe <hi>Maachah</hi> his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother
<pb facs="tcp:5724:40"/>
                  <hi>from her eſtate</hi> becauſe of her idolatrie:<note place="margin">1. King. 15.13.</note> how much more neceſſarie is it for Gods Church that Papiſts be put downe, becauſe of their Poperie? And if any man thinke that Poperie is not idolatrie, the ſame man (there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now no time to debate this cauſe otherwiſe muſt alſo thinke of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that our religion is not Gods ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p>Now followeth the ſixth and laſt concluſion out of this text, that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> ſhould be brought into bondage, that the enemies of the church ſhould be held downe. As it appeareth by the lawe of God,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 23.12, 13.</note> that when the Lord in mercie bringeth them in ſubiection, they ought to be helde in ſubiection. So as they may in no ſort breake the yoke and relinquiſh their obedience, much leſſe preuaile ouer vs, and vſurpe any priuiledge. And to this purpoſe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that it is a point of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>to</hi> (<hi>catter the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 20, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>and to
<pb facs="tcp:5724:41"/>cauſe the wheele to turne ouer them.</hi> And king <hi>Dauid</hi> voweth, <hi>Betimes will I deſtroy all the wicked of the land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that I may cut off all the workers of iniquitie from the Citie of the Lord.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his vowe ſo was his practiſe, not onely at home,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 8, 1, 2, 14,</note> but alſo amongſt the borderers: for <hi>he ſubdued the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> and deſtroyed the Moabites to the third man, <hi>he put a garriſon in Edom and made them his ſeruants.</hi> By this meanes the throne of righteouſneſſe is eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">Pro. 25, 4.5.</note> as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take the droſſe from the ſiluer, and there ſhall proceede a veſſell for the finer:</hi> So take <hi>away the wicked from the king and his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the other-ſide it is threatned if they be not helde downe,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 23.13.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall be a ſnare and deſtruction vnto you and a whippe on your ſides, and a thorne in your eies till you periſh.</hi> This is the word of God concerning the enemies of the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:41"/>Church. And this is the meanes for the Church of God, to lay hold vpon his bleſſing and promiſe here giuen. For it is incredible elſe to what inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie the enemies wil grow, and how much they would take vpon them. It is chronicled of <hi>Salomon,</hi> that he as it were ſurucied the roll of his recuſants;<note place="margin">2. Chron. 2, 17, 18,</note> 
                  <hi>he numbred all the ſtrangers that were in the land of Iſrael,</hi> and finding them to be <hi>an hundreth and three and fiftie thouſand and ſix hundreth, he ſet ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand of them to the burden, and foureſcore thouſand to hew ſtones in the mountaine,</hi> and the reſt to ouerſee. He was not terrified with that multitude, but thought that if <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly policie held downe Gods people, then he might by godly policie holde downe Gods enemies. And it is the direction of the ſpouſe to his friends to catch both the <hi>Foxes and the cubs that deſtroy the vines.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> Was it not a marueilous arrogant ſpeech of <hi>Aram</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5724:42"/>and Apoſtaticall <hi>Ephraim</hi> to ſay, <hi>let vs go vp againſt Iudah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah 7, 5, 6</note> 
                  <hi>and let vs rouze them and make a breach therein for vs, and ſet a king in the midſt thereof, euen the ſonne of Tabeel,</hi> that is, ſuch a one as ſhall ſet vp idolatrie.</p>
               <p>No leſſe pride then this is in the hearts of Papiſts. They meditate ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things, and are more arrogant them <hi>Iannes</hi> &amp; <hi>Iambres</hi> which reſiſted <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 8</note> For they had <hi>Pharaoh</hi> on their ſides to countenance them. But theſe haue our gratious Queene againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe clemencie they haue moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiouſly abuſed, and are therefore to be well watched that they breake not from vs, and duely ſuppreſſed by thoſe which ought, according to the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her royall authoritie.</p>
               <p>The Lord in the fourth comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ſaith, <hi>That the ſtranger that is in our gates ſhall not breake the Sabboth,</hi> that is, ſhall not be ſuffered to breake it, but ſhall be helde at the leaſt from
<pb facs="tcp:5724:42"/>the manifeſt contempt of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. For (as I ſay) without hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them down by authoritie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truſt repoſed by her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie in the Magiſtrates, it is not to bee hoped that the Lord will holde them downe. For we ſhall be guiltie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of the meanes by which the Lord both ſpiritually and outwardly treadeth downe his enemies, as it is written,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.20</note> 
                  <hi>The God of peace ſhall treade Satan vnder your feete:</hi> marke what he ſaith, <hi>Your feete.</hi> And be ſure of it that if this ſerpent will turne againe and <hi>bruiſe our heele,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3, 15</note> though we tread vpon him, <hi>and breake his head;</hi> that then if we tread not vpon him he wil not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to bite at our heele, but will flie in our face.</p>
               <p>But the Papiſts are inſtant, that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ought not to be offered to their conſciences. This is not other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then hath beene made by he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes of old; yea it is one of the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:43"/>things wherein Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his iudgement. Although it be true indeed, that whoſoeuer ſeemeth to imbrace true religion, if he do it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his conſcience, ſinneth for his conſcience ſake; and on the other ſide, if hee imbrace it not, he ſinneth for the trueths ſake, and ſo ſinneth perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, that is, whatſoeuer he doth, as long as his conſcience is blinded, in which reſpect he ſeemeth to be thruſt vpon his damnation by vrging; yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that here that ſaying ought to take place, that it is <hi>better to admit a miſchiefe then an inconuenience,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this miſchiefe in particular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts is not to bee compared with the inconuenience, that commeth to the whole Church of God by ſuffering them to goe vntied. The adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church ought not to be ſubiect to the conſcience of vnreclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable heretikes, to the hurt of the Church; no more then the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb facs="tcp:5724:43"/>of the common wealth ought to bee ſubiect to the irregularitie of the licentious in anie other kind, to the hurt of the commonwealth. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, obſerue well that that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are vrged, is negatiue, that they ſhall not bee reconcilers or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters. They cannot ſay that this is to vrge their conſcience, when they are preſſed onely with negatiue lawes: for this caſe differeth from that of vrging them to come to the Church &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacraments, which is by the vertue of the affirmatiue lawes exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding onely to other penaltie. But theſe men cannot be content to ſcape with their Recuſancie for a pecuniarie mulct, which they pay to the halues, but doe complaine that violence is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to their conſcience to the perill of their ſoules, except they may bee ſuffered to infect and ſupplant our Church by Maſſing and reconciling. And where they threaten vs with their
<pb facs="tcp:5724:44"/>argument, that Compulſion doth no good, nor worketh anie conuerſion; and therefore better left. It is plaine enough that the ſame conſideration which gaue ſatisfaction to Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> in the ſame point concerning the Donatiſts, may ſatisfie vs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; that as in the common-wealth; ſo in the Church malefactors are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to bee repreſſed for a common good, whether the malefactors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues get good by it or no.</p>
               <p>There are all meanes to be vſed to winne them, and all gentleneſſe and forbearing to be vſed towards thoſe, of whom in godly charitie there is good hope by reaſon of their tractableneſſe. They alſo that are of a quiet diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among them, are not to be procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt with like ſeueritie as the turbulent. So that wee beare in mind what <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith of Serpents,<note place="margin">Plin. natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. hiſtoriae lib. 8. cap. 23</note> 
                  <hi>Vulgatum eſt colorem pleroſque terrae habere qua occultentur:</hi> Moſt of them are of the
<pb facs="tcp:5724:44"/>colour of the earth that they may not be diſcerned: and that ſome of them do gather in their bodies like birds to entice birds. Otherwiſe let there be no fraud,<note place="margin">Iude 22.</note> and then (as Saint <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith) <hi>put a difference.</hi> And whether it bee by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wiſedome or by wiſe loue, let thoſe that can preuaile with them haue their foorth.</p>
               <p>Only let two rules be obſerued: Firſt that their doinges bee warrantable by the word of God: and ſecondly that their heartes bee ſound to the Church of God. For whatſoeuer is don ought to bee done out of our loue to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion already eſtabliſhed to amplifie it in the firſt place, and out of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to our ſeduced brethren to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them in the ſecond place. Where this courſe wil take no place, it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to cary a quick eye and a ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hand in ſuppreſſing the Canaanite that is ſtil in the land. So as our loue to
<pb facs="tcp:5724:45"/>God and our Prince therein may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               <p>But principally let vs haue our part with <hi>Shem,</hi> that conſequently we may ſucceed in dominion ouer <hi>Canaan.</hi> Let vs al holde of our renowmed <hi>Shem</hi> our <hi>Shem</hi> in deed Ieſus Chriſt; to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be all honor and glory now and euermore.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Friendly Reader, I pray, thee mend one fault in the fourth page and 15. line, for <hi>ly,</hi> read <hi>family,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5724:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
